The first of the anemias that we're going to discuss are microcytic anemias.
In a microcytic anemia, the red blood cells are small.
And this size is actually measured by the MCV, or the mean corpuscular volume.
And so the MCV in a microcytic anemia will be less than 80.
Recall that the normal MCV is anywhere between 80 to 100.
And so in a small, when the cells are small, the MCV will be less than 80.
It is useful to have a little bit of an understanding of how the microcytosis occurs.
Because once you understand how the microcytosis occurs, you'll get a better understanding of the causes of microcytic anemia.
So let's go back and remind ourselves that the red blood cell is actually formed from a progenitor cell called the erythroblast.
The erythroblast is basically the cell that produces the red blood cells.
Now relatively speaking, the erythroblast is a large cell.
And it will divide, and then divide, and divide, and divide, and eventually it will produce small red blood cells.
So for example, if this is the erythroblast, it will divide into two cells.
And then it will divide, these two cells will each divide into cells, etc.
And so with each division, the cells become smaller.
And that's important when understanding a microcytic anemia, because it helps us to understand why the microcytosis is occurring.
So in particular, we should recognize that microcytic anemias occur because there is an extra division of the cell.
I.e., the erythroblast undergoes one extra division.
Or why don't we say that the cells, as they're generating from the erythroblast to become mature red blood cells,
they sort of undergo one extra division.
Now the next question we could ask is why.
Why would the red blood cells undergo an extra division?
And the answer, at least the way I think about it, is that microcytic anemia is always a problem of decreased production of hemoglobin.
So in each of the microcytic anemias, the problem is the decreased production of hemoglobin.
Now as the red blood cells are developing, if there is not enough hemoglobin,
one way by which the red blood cells can try to maintain the concentration of hemoglobin within the red blood cell
would be to divide one extra time.
Another way to think about this is that it is as if the red blood cell is trying to produce a nice, pretty, red-pink cell.
And if there is not enough hemoglobin, there will not be enough pink in the cell.
And so the red blood cell will divide one extra time in order to try to maintain its color,
i.e., the concentration of hemoglobin.
Okay, now with that in mind, you then have to understand a little bit of biochemistry
to understand the microcytic anemias.
So let's remind ourselves, what is hemoglobin?
Well, the name gives it away.
It's heme plus globin.
All right, and what is heme?
Heme is basically iron and protoporphyrin.
And so if I were to create just a simple understanding in your mind by doing the following,
I've told you that hemoglobin, we know that it equals heme plus globin.
All right, and you know that heme is essentially composed of iron plus protoporphyrin.
I'm just going to say proto here, P-R-O-T-O.
Then, if you understand this basic biochemistry, it's not hard to recognize the causes of microcytic anemia.
For example, let's say that there is a lack of iron, which is called iron deficiency.
If there's low iron, then there would be low heme.
And if there's low heme, there'll be low hemoglobin.
And if there's low hemoglobin, there'll be a microcytic anemia.
So one cause of a microcytic anemia is iron deficiency anemia.
Another way by which we could get microcytic anemia would be, let's say that there's iron,
but the iron cannot be used because the patient has a chronic inflammatory state,
and therefore the iron is being stored away in the macrophages.
So when iron is locked away in the macrophages, that is called anemia of chronic disease.
And the idea there is that iron is not available for use.
And so therefore, if there's low iron, then there's going to be low heme.
And if there's low heme, then there's going to be low hemoglobin.
And if there's low hemoglobin, there's going to be a microcytic anemia.
And so the second cause of microcytic anemia is actually anemia of chronic disease.
The third cause is any circumstance that would decrease the production of protoporphyrin.
And so the disease in which, or the anemia in which there is a decreased production of protoporphyrin,
is called sideroblastic anemia.
And so in sideroblastic anemia, there's low protoporphyrin, which results in low heme.
Low heme results in low hemoglobin.
And low hemoglobin then results in a microcytic anemia.
And then finally, the fourth cause of microcytic anemia is thalassemia.
And what's thalassemia?
Thalassemia is when there's decreased production of the globin chain.
Obviously, decreased production of the globin chain would result in decreased hemoglobin,
and decreased hemoglobin would result in a microcytic anemia.
So actually, this is not hard, if you understand a little bit of basic biochemistry.
And there really are four major causes of microcytic anemia.
Iron deficiency anemia, anemia of chronic disease, sideroblastic anemia, and thalassemia.
Now that's the global picture that you have to have sort of in your mind.
And if you keep this picture in your mind, you'll be very comfortable when dealing with microcytic anemias.
There are, of course, some details that we have to be familiar with.
And so we're going to spend the remainder of our time in this section now walking through each of these anemias individually and highlighting some important high yield principles.
So the first of the anemias that we want to discuss is iron deficiency anemia.
Iron deficiency anemia is due to decreased levels of iron within the body.
This is the most common type of anemia.
Lack of iron is actually the most common nutritional deficiency in the world.
The WHO estimates that approximately one-third of the entire world's population is deficient in iron.
And so iron deficiency anemia is something that all of us are going to encounter in our patients.
Now a little bit about the biochemistry of iron.
You do need to understand it to understand some of the high yields for this disease.
Iron is consumed in both heme, which is meat-derived, and non-heme, which is vegetable-derived, forms.
And the heme form, i.e. the meat-derived form, is more readily absorbed.
Absorption, of course, occurs in the duodenum.
You do need to know that.
Absorption occurs in the duodenum.
And it's the enterocyte.
Recall that the enterocyte histologically is the cell that lines the villi of the duodenum.
The enterocyte regulates the absorption of iron.
Basically, the enterocyte takes up iron from the gut
and then has the ability to transport it into the blood via a transporter called ferroportin.
Now let me draw this for you.
Let's pretend that this is the enterocyte.
And this is the lumen of the gut.
And over here would be a blood vessel.
The enterocyte basically takes up iron from the gut.
And then it makes a decision.
It decides, should I send iron into the blood or not?
The transporter that it uses to move iron from the enterocyte into the blood is called ferroportin.
Ferroportin.
And this is a key regulatory step in iron biochemistry.
The idea here is that the body has the ability to take up iron
but does not have the ability to get rid of iron.
There really is no way for the body to get rid of iron.
Now it's true that a little bit of iron gets lost when the skin is turning over.
And so as skin sloughs off the human being, iron is lost.
A tiny bit of iron is lost.
And it's also true that a female loses iron through the menstrual cycle.
However, generally speaking, physiologically,
the human body does not really have a way of getting rid of iron.
And so you only want to bring in iron when it's needed by the body.
And you don't want to allow excess iron to come into the body.
And so the enterocyte plays that important role of deciding whether or not iron should go into the blood.
And it uses ferroportin to make that decision.
So ferroportin is the key transporter that takes iron from the enterocyte and places it into the blood.
Now once iron gets into the blood, it's always bound.
Remember that iron has the ability to generate free radicals, so it will never be left alone.
It will always be bound to something.
In the blood, it's bound to a molecule called transferrin.
And transferrin transports iron and then delivers it to the liver and to the bone marrow macrophages for storage.
Once iron gets to the liver or the bone marrow macrophages, it's stored in the cell, but it's stored bound to ferritin.
So ferritin is the key molecule to which iron is bound when it is being stored.
And again, it's important to keep iron bound to ferritin because that binding prevents iron from generating free radicals via the Fenton reaction.
And we covered that in detail when we talked about free radicals in Chapter 1 of this text.
Now there are some laboratory measurements that allow you to determine the iron status of a patient.
And these are very high yield to be familiar with.
Both clinically they're useful and obviously on examinations.
So let's walk through them.
Now maybe it would be best to go back and just create a simple diagram so we can see what we're actually measuring.
So again, the idea here is that if you have iron in the blood, so this is the blood vessel,
iron in the blood is going to be bound to a molecule called transferrin.
Now generally speaking, for every three transferrin molecules, one, two, let's make a third one here,
for every three transferrin molecules, one of those transferrin molecules will be carrying an iron.
Eventually that iron is delivered to the macrophage, so let's call this the macrophage.
And when iron is present within the macrophage, iron is bound to ferritin.
So we'll connect it to ferritin over here.
Based on this understanding that I've sort of put here on the screen, we can measure a few pieces of information.
So for example, if we want to know how much iron is in the blood, we can measure the serum iron.
If we want to know how much iron is in the blood, we can measure the serum iron.
If we want to know how many transferrin molecules are present in the blood, whether they be bound or not doesn't matter.
If we want to know how many transferrin molecules are present in the blood,
we can measure something called the TIBC, which is the total iron binding capacity.
It tells you how many transferrin molecules are present in the blood.
If you want to know how many of the transferrin molecules are actually bound by iron,
we can calculate a percent saturation.
Finally, if you want to know how much iron is present in the storage sites, you can measure a serum ferritin.
And so ferritin would tell us how much iron is actually present in the bone marrow macrophages and within the liver.
So these are four key measurements, and they're going to come into play as we move forward in this discussion.
Now when we think about iron deficiency, we should understand that deficiency can be caused by a dietary lack or blood loss.
These are the two sort of common etiologies of how a patient can become iron deficient.
And it's in the context of these two etiologies that I like to think of iron deficiency according to the individual subsets of patients.
So for example, in an infant, an important cause of iron deficiency would be breastfeeding.
And that's because breast milk contains little to no iron.
And so infants can become iron deficient when they're breastfeeding.
In a child, iron deficiency can arise if there's a poor diet.
And so children, they're growing, they need iron, and sometimes the diet is not appropriate for that growth.
And so children can become iron deficient due to poor diet.
In adults, important classic causes of iron deficiency in a male, you think about peptic ulcer disease.
That's actually the most common cause in a middle-aged male.
And the most common cause in a middle-aged female would be menorrhagia, which is heavy menstrual bleeding, in which iron would be lost because blood is lost.
Or pregnancy.
In pregnancy, a woman needs a large amount of iron to grow the fetus.
And so these are two common causes in middle-aged adults.
In older adults, common causes in the Western world are colon polyps or carcinoma.
And in older adults, the most common cause in the developing world is actually a hookworm.
And if we go back to microbiology, recall that the two hookworms to be familiar with, one is a nicator, and the other is ancelostoma.
And so nicator and ancelostoma are two hookworms that are common causes of iron deficiency, again, because of the blood loss associated with hookworms.
These are common causes of iron deficiency in the developing world.
There are some other causes to be aware of.
Obviously, malnutrition could result in iron deficiency, but we kind of highlighted that with the notion of poor diet in a child.
Malabsorption could result in iron deficiency.
Let's say that a patient has a disease that disrupts the duodenum, like celiac disease, in which the villi of the duodenum are destroyed.
That can result in a certain degree of malabsorption.
And if there's malabsorption, the patient could obviously become iron deficient.
And then a third example would be gastrectomy.
And this actually is a kind of high-yield example.
And the reason this is high-yield is because it goes back to a little bit of biochemistry concerning iron.
And that is that iron can be present in an Fe2-plus state.
It can also be present in an Fe3-plus state.
And it's the Fe2-plus that is better, that is more easily absorbed by the body.
And the way I remember that, a little funny, but the way I remember that is Fe2 goes into the body.
Fe2 goes into the body.
Why is that important for this discussion of gastrectomy?
Well, the idea is that acid maintains the Fe2-plus state.
And so if there is acidity, the Fe2 remains in the two, the iron remains in the two-plus state.
And by remaining in the two-plus state, it's more readily absorbed.
Gastrectomy, where a patient would lose part of the stomach, may result in decreased acid.
And the decreased acid would result in decreased bioavailability of iron
because less iron would be in the two-plus state.
So this becomes important, again, because it ties into a little bit of biochemistry.
When a patient becomes iron deficient, they actually go through a series of phases.
And it's nice to understand these phases or stages because they will help you to better understand what's going on in iron deficiency.
So I'm actually going to take a moment to walk you through each of these.
Now, the very first thing, let's pretend that there's a normal patient, and they've got normal iron, and they're doing fine.
And then let's say that the patient, I don't know, they get a hookworm infection, and so now they're starting to lose blood.
So what's going to happen is that initially, as the bone marrow is trying to make red blood cells,
it's going to use up the stored iron.
That's the very first thing that it will do when there isn't sufficient iron being brought into the body.
So over time, the very early stage of iron deficiency is that the storage iron will be depleted.
Now recall, what is the measure of storage iron?
Ferritin.
Ferritin tells you how much iron is stored in the body.
Now, when the storage iron is depleted, what is going to happen to the ferritin, the serum ferritin?
Then the serum ferritin is going to go down, correct?
Because the storage iron is being consumed.
And as the serum ferritin goes down, one of the other things to bear in mind is that sort of always opposite of what ferritin does is TIBC.
So whenever the ferritin goes down, the total iron binding capacity is going to go up.
And what is the total iron binding capacity measuring again?
It's measuring transferrin.
This sort of makes sense in my mind.
Whenever the ferritin is down, then the macrophages and the liver will sort of recognize that the ferritin is down,
particularly because one of the storage sites of iron is the liver.
And then the liver will begin to pump out more transferrin molecules to go and try to find more iron.
And so any time the ferritin goes down, the TIBC, which is a measure of the number of transferrin molecules, will go up.
General principle, always, when the ferritin goes down, the TIBC will go up.
So that's really the first stage of iron deficiency.
Once the stored iron is used, then the next thing that's going to happen is the serum iron is going to be consumed.
And as the serum iron is going to be consumed, a few things are going to happen according to your laboratory studies.
Number one, the serum iron will go down because as serum iron is being used, obviously its levels are going to go down.
And number two, the percent saturation of iron will actually also go down.
Now the way to remember this is to just think about it.
So let's remind ourselves that if you have transferrin molecules, okay, let's draw here six transferrin molecules.
So one, two, three, four, five, six.
We've got six transferrin molecules, correct?
Now normally, when you think about transferrin, one out of every three is bound to iron.
So one out of every three is bound to iron.
So it looks like this.
Now if one out of every three is bound to iron, then what's the normal percent saturation?
Well, in this particular case, we've got two molecules of iron and six molecules of transferrin.
So the current saturation, I'm going to draw it up here in the left-hand side of your slide, is going to be two over six,
which really equals one-third, which equals 33%, which is the normal percent saturation.
All right, so the normal percent saturation is 33%.
Now let's assume that the patient is becoming iron deficient and the serum iron is depleted.
Well, if this iron molecule is consumed, now only one out of six transferrin molecules is bound by iron.
And so one over six equals, you know, 16%, roughly.
And so you can see that the percent saturation has gone down.
When serum iron is depleted, the serum iron will go down and the percent saturation will also go down.
So that's the next phase of iron deficiency.
Now the third stage or phase of iron deficiency is normalcytic anemia.
So what's the idea here?
Now as iron is being depleted from the storage sites and as iron is being depleted from the serum,
the bone marrow is still going to continue to try to make red blood cells.
And in order to make red blood cells, it needs to produce heme.
And in order to produce heme, it's going to need iron.
And so as the bone marrow begins to recognize that iron isn't available, it'll make a sacrifice.
It'll say, I prefer to make normal red blood cells.
I want nice, pretty, red, beautiful red blood cells.
However, because I can't make as many as I would like, I'll just make less.
And so initially, the patient will actually get a normalcytic anemia.
The cells will be normal in size, but there will be less of them made.
And so the patient will actually develop a normalcytic anemia.
The very early stage of iron deficiency anemia is actually normalcytic.
And examiners like you to know that because they want you to understand the sequence of what's going on.
And by the way, clinically, this is important as well.
Because you may find patients in your practice that are in very early stages of iron deficiency,
then you need to know that the initial stage of iron deficiency is actually a normalcytic anemia.
Now, eventually what will happen is the anemia or the iron deficiency will become so severe
that the patient will then develop the inability to produce normal red blood cells.
And so now the bone marrow will be forced to pump out cells that are smaller than normal
and that have less hemoglobin than normal and smaller than normal because they will have undergone an extra division.
And so these would be microcytic, i.e. smaller than normal, and hypochromic.
Hypochromic means that they contain less color than they normally should have.
And remember that when you consider the color of a red blood cell,
the normal red blood cell has a central area of pallor.
That central area of pallor will become expanded so that more of the red blood cell
does not have the red color of hemoglobin.
And so you get a microcytic hypochromic anemia.
And these are the key stages of iron deficiency.
Now, let's go through and remind ourselves of a couple clinical features of iron deficiency.
Obviously, the patients will become anemic.
Another finding, clinically, would be that the patients would have choelonychia,
which is sort of spoon-shaped nails.
And then they can have pica.
And what's pica?
Pica is an abnormality in which patients begin to chew on things abnormally,
like they may chew on dirt, they may chew on ice.
And the way I think about it is sort of a psychological drive to get iron from any source possible,
chewing on dirt, perhaps seeking iron within dirt, for example.
So that's called pica.
Now, what are the key laboratory findings in iron deficiency anemia?
Well, you know that they're going to have a microcytic,
so the MTV would be less than 80, hypochromic, the red cells will look less pink than they should,
with an increased RDW.
Now, this requires a little bit of discussion.
What is the RDW?
The RDW stands for the Red Blood Cell Distribution Width.
Red Blood Cell Distribution Width.
And basically, what the RDW measures is what is the spectrum of size of the red blood cells.
If all of the red blood cells are relatively the same size, then the RDW would be low.
And if there's a wide spectrum of red blood cell size, then the RDW would be high.
Now, in an iron deficiency anemia, recall that the initial phase of the bone marrow response to iron deficiency
is to try to make as many normal cells as possible.
And then, once the iron deficiency progresses, it will begin to make smaller cells.
So there's going to be a spectrum.
There's going to be some normal cells, and there's going to be some small cells.
And so that spectrum of normal cells and small cells is going to widen the distribution of the size of the red blood cells.
And so the RDW is going to increase because of this broad spectrum of varying sizes of the red blood cells.
So that's important to know.
It's classically seen in iron deficiency anemia.
Now, patients with iron deficiency anemia, let's think about this for a minute.
Their serum ferritin, sorry, their iron stores are going to be low, correct?
Because they're using up the iron, so the serum ferritin will be down.
Anytime the serum ferritin is down, the TIBC is going to be up, i.e., the liver will produce more transferrin molecules.
And so that's the measure of the TIBC.
Again, the serum iron will go down because the serum iron will be used.
And when the serum iron goes down, the percent saturation will also go down.
This I've kind of explained previously, so we don't need much detail here.
One aspect of lab findings that I haven't talked about is the free erythrocyte protoporphyrin.
And this actually is very high yield to be familiar with.
And it's actually a decent test for iron deficiency anemia.
And it's also a very good examiner's question because it takes you back to a little bit of biochemistry.
Now, what do I mean by the free erythrocyte protoporphyrin?
Recall that basically heme, correct, this is heme, heme consists of two components.
It consists of iron plus protoporphyrin.
In an iron deficiency anemia, the iron is down.
But is there any problem in iron deficiency anemia with the production of protoporphyrin?
The answer is no.
The protoporphyrin is normal.
And so if iron is down and the protoporphyrin is normal,
some of the protoporphyrin in the red blood cell will not be bound to iron.
It will be floating around free because there isn't iron to bind it to actually produce heme.
And so in the red blood cell, there will be free erythrocyte protoporphyrin.
And so that, again, is very high yield.
One, clinically it's useful.
And two, it allows examiners to test you on some integrated biochemistry
in the context of clinical findings and pathology.
So this is something to be well aware of.
Here's a classic blood smear from a patient with iron deficiency anemia.
And there's a few things to remind ourselves here.
Number one, this is a lymphocyte.
And the nucleus of the lymphocyte should represent the normal size of the red blood cell.
So red blood cells should normally be about the size of the nucleus of the lymphocyte.
And in this particular case, we can see that the red blood cells are small.
And some of them may be close to normal.
But there is a spectrum.
But there certainly are an increased number of small red blood cells.
And so this picture is highlighting for you a microcytic hypochromic anemia,
which would classically be the description of an iron deficiency anemia.
Treatment of iron deficiency anemia is very straightforward.
We give ferrous sulfate.
And the idea here is that we want to replace the iron.
However, remember that if there's some underlying cause that would explain the patient's iron deficiency anemia,
you need to treat that as well.
So, for example, if there's an older male and he has iron deficiency anemia,
it's very important to rule out colonic carcinoma in that patient.
So we don't simply just sort of figure out that there's an iron deficiency anemia and then give iron.
We need to ask the question, why?
Why is the patient iron deficient?
And that's important because if there's a cancer, we certainly want to detect it and treat that as well.
One associated syndrome to be familiar with, it's relatively high yield,
and so we're going to throw it in the context of this discussion.
It's called the Plummer-Vincent syndrome.
This is iron deficiency anemia that has an additional association of esophageal web and atrophic glossitis,
such that the patients present with anemia, dysphagia, and a beefy red tongue.
Let me just highlight what an esophageal web is to make this discussion a little more clear.
This is the esophagus.
You know that the esophagus is lined by a mucosa,
and the mucosa would be relatively tight up against the lumen of the esophagus.
However, there can be redundancy in the mucosa so that some of the mucosa outfolds in this way,
and that could potentially create an obstruction or a partial obstruction within the esophagus.
And so, for example, if a patient were to try to consume foods, in particular poorly chewed foods,
then these foods could actually get stuck as it's trying to move down the esophagus, resulting in dysphagia.
So this mucosal protrusion is called an esophageal web,
and esophageal webs can be seen in many circumstances,
but they're highly associated with Plummer-Vincent syndrome, especially on examinations.